[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net sc radio is brought to you
by the ieee computer society by ieee
software magazine
online at computer.org software
developers are you ready it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris choose your language
choose your tools choose your
environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
when you can make faster decisions
there's no telling what you'll create
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host akshay manchali
my guest today is ryan singer and we're
going to talk about remote work
ryan is the head of product strategy at
base camp he's the author of the book
shape up stop running in circles and
ship work that matters
which explains basecamp's software
delivery process he was previously on sc
radio to talk about just that
back in 2019 on episode 389 ryan welcome
back to the show
hey thanks for having me ryan given that
a lot of people are working remotely and
with your long experience in remote work
uh what are the biggest transitions that
one would go through to start working
remote
it's an interesting question because for
us we we didn't have to make a
transition we've been remote for
you know 20 years now and
so it's something that we're used to you
know i think that the transition to make
is actually
it's interesting the mistakes we make
when we go remote
are actually the same mistakes that we
make when we work together into the
office
when we're all in the office we too
easily
get into a room and have a meeting when
we need to solve something
and when we're remote we too quickly
reach for something like the video call
or the zoom
to to to figure something out and and
it's actually the same problems
happening in both places
which is that we are not uh using enough
asynchronous communication
and that we tend to just sort of get
everybody together to talk
instead of thinking through kind of what
we're trying to do
on our own time in advance you know so
that's that's the big
i think that's the big most important
shift to figure out actually
is how do we start to
plate things up for each other so that
people
can think through things and respond to
things
in the little slices of time that they
have in their day
without having to line up everybody's
day so that we're all talking at the
exact same time
and that gives us the room that we need
in the middle of our day to actually
have those few hours where we can put
our heads down and actually do the deep
difficult work that requires the
concentration and then when we naturally
have those times in our day where
we're not very concentrated or we are
kind of bored or you know we're taking a
break or whatever
that's the right moment to go check the
messages and respond to things and
everybody's going to have those moments
at different times
so we want to figure out how do we
change the way that we communicate so
that everybody communicates when it's a
good time for them
without forcing everybody else to be on
the same schedule
so communication really is a large part
of our
work culture and you know those emails
as meetings
there's there's in-person conversations
there are conversations that you have in
passing
how do you classify these things and how
do you actually go about
thinking about what is an essential
face-to-face meeting
uh and what is asynchronous and what how
do you think about that
that's a great question the general
approach we have
is to start with asynchronous and then
escalate to synchronous
so uh we don't have any meetings
that are kind of repeated or regular on
the schedule
we only call a meeting when we have
something that
happened that now requires us to do some
kind of problem solving together
and so that's a big part of it is we're
asynchronous by default
but i think i think an important thing
to know when it comes to being
asynchronous is that
you know the only way that you can be
asynchronous is if you know what you're
what you have to do if nobody knows
what's going on and nobody knows what's
happening and nobody knows what to do
next
then you have this like big cloud of
confusion
and the only way to get out of that is
to get together and everybody updates
each other and then says okay what are
you doing what am i doing what's
happening and then you become clear
right we need to take some other steps
so that
everybody actually knows what's going on
we know individually what it is that we
should be working on and how we
contribute and what we're waiting for
from other people
you know so a lot of that has to do with
the fact that
we are very deliberate about how we
frame and shape the work that we're
going to take on and who's doing what
we're very clear
about who's doing what work and that
allows us to
sort of separate from each other you
know
and and so i think it's really important
to figure out how to be more deliberate
about what we're doing instead of just
kind of wandering
and and and syncing up again day after
day
so in other words there's a there's a
larger ramp up time that might require
face-to-face communication and
synchronous communication and from there
on
you can take it asynchronously is that
what you mean by trying to
understand what everyone is up to so i
think it helps to get into the details
of
of of what your role is and what kind of
work you do and what kind of
communication you need
because depending on your role you're
gonna you're going to need to coordinate
with people in different ways
so for example we follow the the
the process that i outlined in the book
shape up and
in that process we've got teams who are
working
within the six week cycle so these are
designers and developers
and people doing qa and then we've also
got people on the leadership side
who are figuring out what we should do
next and and shaping the work
and um and that's all kind of within the
sort of product side of things of course
there's also ops
and there's and there's security
infrastructure performance there's other
teams doing other things
when it comes to for example the betting
table where we choose what projects
we're going to take on in the next cycle
we don't have very much uh synchronous
back and forth there's a lot of
kind of individual preparation jason is
going to have ideas about what we should
do next david's going to have ideas i'm
going to have ideas and we're each going
to be
working on those and preparing those as
pitches i might be far into a pitch
and i might have a really crucial
question
about whether or not this is viable or
whether i'm thinking about it in the
right way
and then i might ask jason to talk it
over with me
so then we're going to have a one-on-one
where we're going to talk that through
right
but other than that we're working very
independently but then when it comes
time to actually make the
decisions about what goes into the next
cycle
that's going to be a call right so we
have a kind of a clear time
we're going to get in a call together
and we're going to work that out then
there's an announcement made to the
teams and that announcement is written
so the teams can see all the work that's
coming and they can see the shaping that
was done
as as write-ups and also by the way when
we have that betting table conversation
there's pitches that are written that
everybody reads beforehand so it's not
like you're going in blank
and then you're seeing a bunch of
presentations or something like that
there's a lot of written
asynchronous communication that leads up
as the preparation to that
but then when we when we come to handing
it off to the team
there's a write-up that describes what's
going on and then the team gets a chance
to absorb that
then there's going to be a kick-off call
which is an opportunity to ask questions
and clarify things
and then from then on for the whole
cycle
the team is basically working
asynchronously and
what we'll often see is a little bit of
light coordination in the chat room
at the beginning of the cycle because
there needs to be a little bit of hey
i'm gonna go explore
the ui for this and i'm gonna go spike
some back end for that and then let's
let's check in tomorrow and see where
we're at right but that's happening
that's happening
you know it's funny how chat is kind of
synchronous but it's sort of like
loose slightly asynchronous when you
have when you have only like three
people
you know there can be a little bit of
lag time between answering so there's
some nice flexibility there
and then what's going to happen is the
teams are going to be very heads down
and they're going to be posting things
onto to do messages in basecamp which
have comment threads attached
and those enable actually kind of slow
asynchronous updates if there's
questions or back and forth on a piece
of work that can happen
inside of the to-do and then it might
happen that after a week or two of work
some kind of a substantial question
comes up right about
are we pursuing this in the right way or
there's a difficult trade-off that they
didn't expect
and then they might reach out to
somebody to
to say hey can we talk this through and
then you're having a meeting
but it's not really a meeting it's more
like you're working
you know so i really like to distinguish
the
the the types of calls where you get a
whole bunch of people together and then
most people are sitting around
and people are just kind of updating
each other or trying to figure out what
to do
versus having a kind of work session
you know where there's a defined problem
and you bring a couple people who have
the right expertise
and then you work together to sort of
solve it so i would say actually the
majority of the
kind of quote unquote meetings that we
have are more
like where we're actually workshopping
something you know
you have just just a couple people who
are the right people
and they're applying their expertise to
get unblocked on on some kind of a
problem or come to a conclusion about
something
that's really interesting you mentioned
that initially
you do a lot of upfront planning and
that makes sense if you're coming from a
leadership position
and uh depending on your role right but
how do you
uh junior engineers or people with uh
lower experience who are not in
leadership roles
how do they effectively sort of go with
planning or
get prepared towards you know not having
these meetings to
understand what they're going to work on
or what they would like to work on etc
this is where the shaping is essential
if we
are shaping the work before we give it
to a team
then the team has these clear boundaries
they're like hard walls around the
outside of the work that say this is
these are the problems to solve this is
what's in and this is what's out
and this is what needs to get figured
out over the course of the next six
weeks
so it's the combination of having the
shaping already done
and having that clear deadline that
actually this isn't just working two
weeks at a time two weeks at a time two
weeks at a time
there's back pressure coming from the
end of that six weeks
because we have this what we call the
circuit breaker if the project doesn't
ship at the end of the six weeks by
default it actually doesn't get an
extension
so that means that the teams have to
make trade-offs and say how am i going
to solve this problem
right but they're not just wandering
out in the wilderness without knowing
where to go because they have the walls
from the
from the work that was shaped so that's
really the big difference is when they
have that clarity
of what it is that they're supposed to
be doing then they can just focus all of
their attention on
how do i actually do that and that's
very enabling then
you don't need to have a lot of meetings
or planning or anything like that
because
the work is there and then you just dive
in
interesting so on the team of
communication
there's a lot of large meetings that are
top-down communication
and large organizations you know like
all hands and
uh leadership calls and things like that
how do you guys deal with those kinds of
communication is that also written yes
that's written
you know i anything especially that is
that has the character of an
announcement is better written
because then you can you can very
carefully prepare it you can describe
everything that needs to be there and
then people can read it on their own
time when they have the chance to do
that
and then if if because of the nature of
the thing
you need to have some kind of
opportunity for questions of
clarification
first of all that could happen
asynchronously as
a discussion thread but um sometimes
that might not be appropriate especially
if
if there's an aspect which is more
emotional or or socially sensitive to
the subject you know then you may want
to
be able to to to hear each other's
voices and show body language as you as
you as you talk through it
but still in in that situation i think
it would be better to start off
asynchronous with the clear write up
and then schedule a q a you know as uh
if anybody has questions and wants to
discuss this here's an opportunity to
to do that as a separate thing what
about uh just general small talk between
uh
co-workers you know if i'm i i usually
work out of the office
and i enjoy my conversations with some
of my co-workers who sit nearby you know
just finding out what they're up to
it's not necessarily um communication
that gets work done but it's kind of
like communication to get to know the
person and what they're up to
and associating yourself with a broader
organization
so how does base camp go about some of
those uh aspects
that's the most difficult part of being
remote you know
you you can't have everything for free
you know you have to make some
trade-offs and unfortunately i think
the serendipity the unexpected
conversations
you know those those are the things that
are the hardest
you can't really replace them i i don't
think and so
you know we do our best we have a couple
mechanisms the
the basically three things
help with that and none of them are a
replacement for the serendipity you get
in office but like i said you have to
make a trade off
the first thing is we do have the chat
rooms
in base camp they're called campfires
and every project or team has them
and we're very clear about something so
anything that
has to do with decision making
anything that has to do with with the
work
unless you're in a really small team of
two or three people
you know that doesn't happen in chat
because chat is something that just
scrolls away
and nobody should be expected to be
monitoring the chat all day
to catch everything that happens there
you know nobody will be able to get
anything done if they have to watch the
chat room all day
so but if you have an understanding that
the chat room is a place
to just talk and goof around and share
things with each other
and you don't need to follow it right
but if you want to just chit chat with
people
that is actually a really good place
it's actually much better for
socializing than it is for working
you know and and i think that's a very
good distinction to have that it's
everything in chat is optional it's a
good place to socialize
the other thing is we have a feature in
base camp called automatic check-ins
and the automatic check-in basically
notifies everybody
at the end of the day that says hey what
have you done recently
and then we have a kind of convention
for how we answer that people just write
a few bullet points that describe some
things that they've done recently
and this is a nice way for everyone to
have an
ambient knowledge of who's doing what
without having stand-up meetings so i
have a
rough sense of what basically everybody
in the company
who's writing these updates is kind of
working on what problems they're in
or what you know what projects they're
doing and that's that's all happening
asynchronously and people just answer
that when they have time either every
day
or every two days they'll answer and
that just kind of bubbles up to
everybody so that creates a kind of
ambient awareness
we actually have the same type of
automatic check-in
for a few social things which is also
helps a little bit like so we have one
called
what did you what did you do this
weekend and it comes up on monday
morning
and then people share photos of you know
what they did with the garden or where
they went with the family
or some some something that they cooked
or whatever you know
and it's it's a nice way to just sort of
share some things like that with each
other so we have a lot of things like
that
um so the automatic check-ins are good
for that and then the third thing
is i actually think that the sort of
regularly scheduled how do i say this
kind of infrequent slightly random
one-on-ones over video are really useful
so they don't quite capture the
serendipity of passing by each other in
the office but
uh it's it's a nice way to sort of
randomly sample the network
you know you have like 50 people in the
company and everybody's connected in
different ways and and and
everybody sort of naturally talks to
certain people in their neighborhood
around them but if you can kind of
randomly schedule
have a one-on-one with somebody that you
don't talk to so often and there's no
agenda
right it can be very surprising the
things that come up out of that
right it can turn out you know i just
heard this interesting thing from the
customer oh we were just working on this
thing a couple weeks ago oh
i hadn't even thought about that that's
a really interesting idea you know and
then things can kind of click like that
so those three i think using the using
the chat not for real work but for
socializing
having the automatic check-ins to have a
sort of ambient
understanding of what's going on with
other people and then kind of
you know once a month a one-on-one with
somebody from a different department
and then kind of shaking that up with
who you talk to is a nice way to
sort of have some of that that sort of
random deeper
interaction yeah the transparency about
what you're working on is is really
interesting that you guys do that
so i want to move on to talking about
say collaboration
right so there is certainly now you know
what your plan is
you have to execute this and you want to
collaborate with your teammates um it
could be
whiteboarding brainstorming sessions how
do you go about some of those
processes yeah so inside the cycle
though the way that everybody makes
progress is by building
so we're doing the shaping
before the cycle starts so that the
teams don't have to do
kind of brainstorming and discovery but
that there's there's there's enough
clarity from the walls that are up that
they can just kind of
get in there and start to make stuff and
start to spike so a lot of the
collaboration that happens
within the designers and the developers
is actually
sharing code or sharing a screen that's
in progress
or looking at something it's all real
stuff
you know so there's not it's not a lot
of whiteboarding it's more
here's my first take at that model let's
look at the code here's the pull request
or that kind of a thing you know
and then um for the for the shaping side
of things
then there's there's a there's a certain
amount of deep work
that goes in to trying to understand the
problem
trying to frame maybe we have three
different approaches to something that
we think we want to do and how do we
figure out which one is better and which
one is worse you know
so there's some kind of um kind of deep
work that needs to happen
and then out of that some decision
making or
some some some sort of workshopping
together so sometimes
i'll dig into a problem and i'll do some
customer interviews and i'll review some
research that i've done
and and and whatever i can draw from and
then i'll come to a point where
i think i have a solution that is a
potential pitch
for what we might build in a future
cycle and i'll work on that on my own
and then i might need some kind of
technical feedback
from david or or jeff who's a very very
senior programmer here
because there's something that i don't
understand about how the system works
and what what the implications are for
the back end of this idea that i'm
working on
so then we'll do a video chat and i will
kind of walk them through this is
what i'm thinking this is the motivation
and then here's what i think the
solution is and what's your take on that
right and that could be actually uh kind
of sketching
on an ipad and the ipad is screen shared
in
so it's almost like a virtual whiteboard
experience it could be
just talking it through and then
sometimes we'll get clarity just from
that conversation or sometimes um like
recently i i pitched a a
kind of a very unusual new feature idea
for base camp four
and i shared it with jeff and then jeff
went and he actually dedicated about
three or four hours
to spiking this to see if it was viable
on the in the model the way that he
thought it would like is
the is does the modeling we have is the
modeling we have gonna do what we think
it's gonna do or not so he did a short
three or four hour spike
and then he wrote up his conclusions
asynchronously back
and then it was like okay cool like now
i i can go forward with this right
or there's other times where i'll dig in
and i'll do the research
and i'll think that i kind of have a
direction but i'm not sure
and then jason might be curious based on
my check-ins maybe he heard hey i heard
you were
working on this interesting new idea
about email notifications i want to hear
what you're thinking so then we'll have
a call and there we're kind of earlier
in the process i don't have work product
to show him yet
i don't have a solution to show him yet
but i can say you know i think i'm
understanding the problem
like this and i think we have a
potential to maybe explore this
direction
and then we'll bounce ideas off of each
other like that so it's very it's very
ad hoc
but i think it's also very intentional
it's
we know what we're trying to get out of
the call either i'm trying to get
feedback on a specific idea from someone
who has domain knowledge that i don't
have
or i've i've got an idea about how to
frame the problem but i don't i'm not
close enough to have a solution so then
we're bouncing ideas like that
you know so it's it very much depends on
the circumstance but the key point is
that
it's very intentional and it's very
small we're not bringing
eight ten people together on a call you
know okay
i i can see how uh being deliberate and
intentional
uh works for say system design data
modeling
and some of those aspects but what about
uh
visual design you know how do you
collaborate on say wireframes and
mock-ups it may not be eight people on a
call but it might be two people
iterating on say
what the ui might look like so how do
you guys uh
do some of those kinds of collaborations
yeah that's interesting
so that that happens that's within the
team within the cycle that type of that
level of work
and we actually don't do any wireframing
at basecamp
we think it's the wrong level of
fidelity to work at so the designers
will
stub something so let's say we're
looking at what the web team is doing
the designer working on a web feature
is actually going to put a view together
with some of the basic elements
wired into it and then
they might drop a screenshot into the
chat
or they might make a commit and then say
hey to
reload that screen check it out i put
the i wired the button in there let's
see how it looks right
or i've got a rough version of the form
in place let's see how that is
and then the programmers working with
them might have some feedback
that might happen sort of just back and
forth in the chat
or it could happen that there's a to-do
so the teams together what happens is
the the designers and the programmers
nobody creates tasks for them right we
have we have no kind of task master type
of a role
the work is shaped the team takes on
that work and then they actually
capture the tasks that they discover for
themselves in the project
so the designer might have a task that
says something like
you know design the form right and then
uh when they make some progress on that
they could just attach a screenshot to a
comment on that task
and then if they have some question
about it they could mention somebody
and then loop that in right so very
often actually
uh there isn't a lot of back and forth
it's more about building
and like hey i've got that in right
and it's we we really prioritize getting
the elements
into the code over having the right
design
because the thing is if your code is
clean
and your designers are actually working
directly
in the stack themselves they're not
handing over a high-fidelity mock-up for
somebody else to implement
you don't have to get the design right
in the first shot
you can put the form fields in you can
put the buttons onto the screen
and then if you don't like how it is you
can just move them later
you know what i mean you can continually
adjust like that
so we're much more focused on actually
building real stuff
and making commits uh then we are sort
of discussing the design
right and then there's going to come a
point from time to time where
there's a hard choice to be made or the
designer might feel like ah this just
isn't working or maybe this isn't right
and maybe the designer has a review with
jason
and they look at how it's coming and
then they come up with a new idea for
for how to do it differently right so
there can be kind of review calls like
that that happen from time to time
but again they're very intentional and
they're very
deliberate based on a question that came
up
calling all developers there's no
telling what you can create when you
upgrade your data platform to
intersystems iris
are you ready to build the applications
you want however you want them
are you ready to develop applications
faster than ever collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
enter systems iris data platform ready
set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
on that team about uh checking in code
reviews are one aspect is there
something differently that you do with
code reviews or is that tradition
it is traditionally asynchronous so you
know does that continue or is there
something different that you guys do
yeah so we have a a
a different attitude toward toward code
reviews and also toward anything
basically quality related our general
viewpoint is that
review should not be a gate or a
checkpoint
so we don't want to be cueing up work
that
needs a review in order to move forward
instead
by default we trust the teams
to make good decisions and the teams
have the authority and the autonomy
to make the decisions that they want to
make and then that's what's going to get
shipped at the end of the six weeks
so by default there's actually no review
then based on the opportunities that
appear or the questions that come up
you know let's say david knows that the
team is
is is working on something that's that's
a that's unusual when it comes to the
modeling
right it's something we've never done
before or it's something that touches a
system
that is is a bit complicated
he might be interested in in their
solution
and uh so he might be kind of watching
the the pull request
you know or watching the new commits
come in out of his own interest
and then if he sees something that
uh he has an idea about or he has some
sort of input then he might share that
right or if somebody who is a little bit
more junior
is taking on something that is kind of a
outside of their comfort zone or kind of
a growth opportunity for them
then uh somebody who's more senior who
knows that this that
that this is a this is a sort of an
opportunity where they're being
challenged
is maybe going to take an interest in
how that's going but they're not
necessarily going to say now is your
review or
let's let's do a code review they might
just be paying attention you know
but it could also happen that david is
just busy doing other things
you know what i mean and then he doesn't
pay any attention at all and
whatever ships is whatever ships and
it's totally fine right
and uh and it can also go the other way
where rather than someone's senior
kind of taking an interest and looking
at it uh the person who's doing the work
might raise a raise a hand and say hey
what do you think about this
or you know can i get some input on this
but
it's it's all about sort of we're just
trying to be
convex to the situation we want to have
the opportunity if it's helpful
to create a moment where there's some
training or there's some learning
or there's an improvement of what's
there but
we just capture those opportunities when
they appear and when they seem like a
meaningful use of time
there there's not a a formal process
there where those things have to happen
related to uh how you talk to say junior
engineers how do you mentor
uh your junior engineers uh continuously
through this
software development process or to their
career we have a
beautifully i think old-fashioned
solution to that which is you just work
together
i learned so much at every stage of my
career
just by working next to people who were
better than me
when i first started 17 years ago
when i started to work with jason at
base camp you know we were doing client
projects
and he would kind of assign me some
design work to do
and then we when we would talk it over i
would start to learn
how he thinks just by the things that he
would point out the things that he would
say to me and the patterns that i would
notice
right and then when i started to learn
programming and i
and i saw how david i was in david's
code you know
and i saw how david organized the code
and it was just so educational to just
be seeing
the real work of other people so
just putting people together in teams is
already a
massive kind of learning situation you
know
so if you've got two programmers and a
designer and one of the programmers is a
bit more junior or more new to the
company
and and then the other one is more
experienced then you immediately have a
all kinds of learning that's happening
there and so
i think we see a lot of a lot of
maturity coming
and a lot of of growth coming just from
sort of osmosis like that so when you
say
working together do you have more forms
of synchronous communication where
maybe it's pair programming or maybe you
work together on
your written communication with the
other teams do you actually
do that together the pattern here is
that everything is asynchronous by
default and escalates up
according to the needs of the moment
right
and because we have so few meetings
in general we don't have all of these
sort of regularly scheduled meetings
with a whole bunch of people
it means that and because we're
asynchronous by default
it creates the space for these random
little meetings to happen when they're
actually useful
you know what i mean like if you have so
many meetings all the time
then then if you actually want to talk
to somebody about a real problem that
you have
like one-on-one or there's then then
there's no time for that because
you already had so many meetings and
it's like hey i'm trying to get some
work done and now you on top of it you
want to have this call right
but if you if your calendar is totally
empty
all the time and all you need to do is
work
and respond to messages on your own
schedule and then all of a sudden
you have a question about something
you're doing you could just ping
somebody and say hey can we look at this
together
and then it's actually not difficult to
take that time together
do you know what i mean so it's it's
really about flipping
all of the defaults upside down and then
by
by by creating this free
time in everybody's schedule by being
asynchronous then all of these random
sessions can happen just totally ad hoc
right
and then there's no there's nothing bad
about having a synchronous session or or
pairing maybe even just pairing for the
afternoon on something
but it's not a matter of policy it's not
a matter of
like a periodic plan it's
it's about convexity it's about taking
advantage of a moment that appears
and then having the space and the chance
to actually take advantage of that
that makes a lot of sense i guess i was
going to ask you
how do you collaborate across time zones
but the asynchronous nature
kind of takes care of itself right
exactly and the time zones actually help
you
because they kind of force you to be
more asynchronous you know what i mean
and they give you that
that chan that time where it's not
practical to overlap right and then you
you will naturally kind of tend to do
more of the overlapping type of
communication
when the time zones are overlapping
right so yes that's actually really nice
yeah well that actually sounds great but
uh are there any
things that don't work because of this
uh asynchronous nature
and across time zones it doesn't work if
the time zones don't overlap at all
so you do need to have some overlap
we've learned that that's important
we're i mean working asynchronously
requires
you have to bring some conditions
together for this to work
you have to have the right tooling which
this sounds like an ad for base camp but
it's surprising actually how
few of the tools out there support
long-form asynchronous communication you
know
if you're using something like slack and
trello or then you're in a situation
where
you have a lot of fast churn of messages
on the conveyor belt but you don't have
any way
to post something important that you're
sure everybody will see
right and so there's kind of this weird
gap in a lot of the tooling
between either you have email on one
side
or you have this like chaos
of fast messages on the other side and
there isn't this zone in the middle
so whether i mean you know we we built
base camp
around kind of this zone in the middle
of
a high signal meaningful message
where when you post it you know that the
people you notified are actually going
to see it and find it and read it
and respond to it and it's not just
going to get lost in the shuffle
you know so if you don't use base camp
then then then
look for the the means that you're going
to rely on
to post something that you know other
people are going to see where there's a
question that you need answered
or an announcement that needs to be
understood or something that's going to
impact you know you you need to have a
a way to post that that you're sure
people are going to see it
otherwise if you if a lot of people try
to use something like slack
for for this and what you end up with is
you're either in a zoom call
or you're on slack and it's just this
it's it's really hard to get traction
with the asynchronous communication that
way
you need to get you need something
that's paced at the right speed
to get that traction i guess one way to
look at it would be to
change our mental model with respect to
how we look at different channels on
slack
because a lot of companies kind of use
slack or
just email right so i guess groups on
email or
channels on slack can be more deliberate
with respect to what their expectation
is
they can be deliberate but the problem
is that if you're in a chat room
then the very nature of the medium is
that you have these short little
messages that are just flying by
and it's very difficult to to follow up
on it
the thing is that what what you really
need when you're doing work together
is to have subjects that
specific subjects to the problem that
you're dealing with so
i'm working on this side project right
now and we have a
product that does some algorithmic
clustering of of interview data
and it turned out that the cluster we
used the right clustering algorithm but
we forgot a cert
there was some for some reason the
clusters coming out didn't match
the tooling we were using before and
we're like are we using the wrong
algorithm do we have a wrong setting
this is like the this is the kind of
thing that comes up you know
the the the algorithm isn't doing what
it's doing what it should be doing and
we have to solve this
and this isn't just some chit chatty
stuff this is like the work
right and so what i did is i posted in
base camp
a message and the subject of the message
is
blah blah blah clustering algorithm
there's no
pre-made channel to discuss this problem
you know what i mean it needs its own
place with its own name
so that when it pops up people know what
this conversation is about and it's only
about that one thing
and that's how you get the really high
signal and low noise
in the conversation is because this
conversation is only about this issue
and because you have a dedicated thread
just to that one issue
now the back and forth is very focused
and you reach a point where
you have the solution and then the
threat is over and now you're discussing
somewhere else
so that's that's where a chat tool is
never going to do it for you
and you need you need something that
actually has a a deliberate topic for
what you're talking about in order to
because think about it you need to
manage 10 or 20 of those in parallel
yeah
if you're involved in a lot of work and
there's just no way to know what people
are talking about unless it has
there's a reason emails have subjects
you know i mean so
it's you know yeah well uh what about
things like
learning and development like you know
tech talks maybe
you've come across an interesting
product that you want to talk to your
team or you will come across an
interesting technical paper you want to
discuss with your team
uh how do you guys do that yeah chat is
really good for that kind of a thing
because it comes back into this this yes
or no question
is this um is this a need need to know
for us to do the work or is this a nice
to know
because i want to chat with people if
it's if it's nice to know
no problem just put it in the chat and
then people either check the chat or
they don't
and if they miss it then there's no bad
consequences for the work
if it's a need to know then it has to go
in a place that has higher traction than
chat
right so we see a lot of really good you
know
sharing of links and then check out this
youtube video and here's this cool talk
that i saw and there's a lot of that
happening in chat
all the time and that's great chat is
awesome for exactly that kind of a thing
so when it comes to like say uh
development of your own personal career
right so you want a holistic development
that
involves say presentations being able to
actually speak
up so how does basecamp go about some of
those
you know building some of those skills
in your engineers in a completely remote
environment
how do they build the skills to to go
out and give talks
or or learn new skills or
kind of like a little bit of both really
so in terms of just career progression
and career development
uh in in a fully remote environment uh
you know what do you guys
actually do there so two things first of
all i think
i think we all too easily underrate how
much we learn by working together
with people who are more experienced so
again working side by side or just the
combination of
uh let's say so we so for example we
have a team here called research and
fidelity r deaf
and sam and javon are are the
the two people on that team and they are
amazingly expert in javascript
not only how to do things but also the
level of taste that they bring
the judgment that they bring and the
maturity that they have in their
decision making
is unbelievable and what will happen is
anybody who
is working on some javascript and they
feel
a little bit unsure about their approach
or they would like some review
they will go to sam and javon and ask
them for a review
and and they'll get feedback and then
the amount that you learn from a session
like that is amazing
it's totally amazing it's the same thing
if i go to jason to get some feedback on
a design concept
he's going to have some perspective that
is going to be
not only useful to the problem but i'm
going to be paying attention to like
how was he thinking where was he coming
from when he gave me that advice right
and by doing that repeatedly over time
you have a relationship that's basically
like mentoring
you know and um i think that is where
the real learning happens is through the
human exchange
it over real work when you're in the
context of a real problem and you go and
you say hey
how would you do this or what do you
think about the solution that i'm
pursuing that's that's the real thing
then that's got to be 80 of where real
learning happens
there is a 20 that i think is valuable
as well
where for example i will post
status updates about what i've been
doing but i try to
to go a little bit further than that and
i write almost like blog posts
internally that describe the thought
process that i went through
or the the strategy that i used to come
to a conclusion on something
so um when i do an interview project
with a bunch of customers i won't just
say
here's what i heard from the customers
i'll say like
here's why we did this project at this
time here's how i set up the interviews
here's you know what i mean here's like
here were the interesting questions that
motivated the project and then here's
what we did with this you know so it's
giving people a lot of context and and i
think it's giving people a chance to
kind of learn what product strategy is
as as we're practicing it so far and and
what it actually means for me to do the
kind of work that i'm doing
and then it hopefully invites people in
so that if they're interested in doing a
similar kind of work
they're starting to get some some
footholds and some handholds into aha
okay
these are the steps involved and this is
the kind of thinking involved and and
then
it gives them a chance to to come closer
in other words like as
a senior developer or a senior person
with experience being deliberate about
the how and why you've come across
come to a decision kind of
surfaces that knowledge for someone who
really wants to understand the nuances
without actually
creating a meeting to kind of like do
that is that a fair way to put it
yeah you said that in better words yeah
that's yeah yeah it's like uh
if there's a big decision to be made
then that's a really great opportunity
to write it up
in a way that tells the story of the
decision and and inc
including the the things that were
confusing about the decision or the
things that
where you you struggled along the way
right and then
what methods did you use or which
patterns did you reach for
or what experience did you draw on and
how did you come to a conclusion
and then there's also little things you
know like we have a we have a a designer
named adam who does all of our marketing
design
and he's not only a visual designer but
he is
very much on the cutting edge of like
kind of what the right technology is to
implement
the the designs and he's really good
about he'll share
in his in his updates hey i tried this
new platform before we were using jekyll
and now i'm using this thing called
whatever 11d or whatever it is you know
and then there's some awareness of kind
of what the new tooling is just from
reading his updates like i feel a little
bit more up to speed on
on what the cutting edge is so there's a
lot of knowledge transfer happening
even just asynchronously like that
that's interesting uh
earlier on you mentioned about having
these random one-on-ones with uh
people in the company uh but how do you
go about doing one-on-ones with say your
direct reports uh
if you're a manager or if you're an
engineer you want to have a one-on-one
with
your manager how do you guys structure
some of those
uh regular things that happen in large
companies
yeah i um i'm aware of the fact that
that is happening
but i happen to sit in a weird corner of
the company where
i i don't have direct reports and i'm
collaborating kind of horizontally with
jason and david on things
and then jason and david have the final
call on
the work that i do strategy wise which
what pieces of that work actually become
bets that the teams go and build
so i i have a lot of kind of horizontal
collaboration but i don't have people
that i'm that are reporting to me
so but we have other folks who are doing
that but i'm sorry you'd have to you'd
have to talk to them to get the answer
and how they manage that but
they seem to be managing but i don't
know the mechanics of how they schedule
that
okay that could be asynchronous too in
do you know as far as i understand
there's a they're doing one-on-ones from
time to time
we have uh we have across the whole
company semi-annual performance reviews
and those those of course take the form
of a one-on-one call
but i don't know i don't know the the
regularity of those one-on-ones within
those teams and
and the thing is that our teams are
fairly small
so for example we have jonas who who is
managing
the designers we have jeff who's
managing the programmers
troy is managing the folks in ops each
of them
have people under them but who they
interact with very frequently
so it's not like there's someone that
you never talk to and never see
and then and then you have to sort of
create this artificial time
to interact there's a lot of interaction
happening all the time you know
so uh but we'd have you'd have to talk
to them to get the details
okay i'll link to any resources that i
might find on basecamp's website
sure in the episode i know that jason
and david did a really extensive q and a
on remote working
okay um maybe a month ago and i'm sure
they addressed that at some point in in
that like
maybe two hour uh q a session that was
recorded i could imagine that they have
some answers there
i'll add a link to that so how do you
guys
accommodate stressors outside of work
among your co-workers
um you know people might be going
through a difficult time people might
have
you know children and pets at home
especially right now with the ongoing
pandemic there are a lot of people who
are working
from home who are not used to working
from home but they're working the same
hours right so
how do you guys look at some of those
stressors
and how do you deal with that what i see
jason and david doing is
they are very good at communicating
their expectations and adjusting their
expectations
the way that i see that they've
responded to this change in circumstance
you know before we we like i said we've
been remote for years
but in the in in the present
circumstances
people are all kind of um locked locked
down in the home
with the whole family which means that
remote today isn't the same as remote
you know a few months ago and and the
thing that they did
was they said look we know
that you are going to be more distracted
and that you have more things that you
have to handle
with having the kids at home and and
sharing the space with the whole family
all the time throughout the day
and it's not going to be possible to
deliver
the same level of productivity and focus
that you used to
and i think that that was huge
coming from the leadership to say we
don't expect you
to to deliver the same way you did
before right and
and that takes a lot of pressure off you
know versus saying you know do
everything you can and and
and you know it's it created that space
right and i i think we all felt a kind
of
life hasn't gone completely back to
normal because we're still
still especially for the folks who have
kids they're still dealing with that
however
because over a month i don't know how
long it's been but at least a month has
gone by
and um people have found
their their their new routines and their
their mechanisms for how to work around
things you know it's like you figure out
how to
how to take the phone call on the
balcony instead of you know like
yeah you have to figure out where to go
to have that privacy or or whatever you
know
people have been figuring that out and
then you start to see okay
it it seems like uh you know we still
need to make an allowance for the
change in circumstance but it's not
quite as extreme as before and we can
adjust the expectations up again
and i remember seeing a post from jason
and david more recently
that said hey it looks like people are
kind of figuring it out a little bit
more things start to feel a little bit
more normal so
you know we're going to bring this and
that back into the picture again
and so they've been really good at at
just taking responsibility for that
for for setting the expectations it's so
typically you know outside of the
pandemic how do you take care of your
well-being
uh what do you do to stay active healthy
uh how do
other people in the company look at that
uh what are your thoughts around you
know
remote work and just well-being yeah so
the first thing
um i think everybody has different
struggles when it comes to this for me
i found it really helpful to first of
all identify that
so for the type of work that i'm doing i
i'm not answering tickets all day
if you know it's it's different if you
if you're doing creative work if you're
doing problem solving work versus if
you're doing something like support
where you you have to be re responsive
to a cue
in my case and i think for a lot of
people who are doing development and
design
there's a certain sense that every day
you should move the project forward
where you should have some new work that
got completed
but at the same time there isn't there
shouldn't be an expectation that
you know for eight hours a day all
you're doing is coding
you know because a mixture of your time
goes toward
catching up on the asynchronous
communication there's going to be
a little bit of i just feel distracted
right now so i'm gonna like
look at youtube you know there's this a
mixture of of of
of moods and moments throughout the day
for me i i try to make sure that every
day i get
into that place that focused
concentrated place
where you know three hours go by
and i and i and i forgot about the world
and
and i i really substantially moved
forward on that thing that i'm working
on today
you know and if i get a three-hour chunk
of time like that every day
and then the rest of the day i kind of
catch up with people and nibble at
different things
i feel pretty productive and and i think
being honest
about about the the different types of
work that happen is is helpful so that
you don't
beat yourself up because the whole day
went by and
and you didn't get this or that done
right yeah and then
um for me i find it helpful to kind of
create different rituals
that allow me to get into that zone so
different people have different times of
day where they
are more naturally in a flow and for me
i it's never worked well for me to get
up and then first thing in the morning
kind of go deep into the work
i i like to sort of wander around and
catch up on things in the morning and
and read this and read that and so on
and then for me it's always been kind of
after lunch is that moment where
like now i will buckle down and i will
solve that design problem that i
promised myself i would solve today or i
will
you know build that screen that i was
going to build or whatever it was
and um i find it really helpful to kind
of like change
my location in connection with that
shift you know so i might be home at my
desk in the morning
and having video calls i like to
schedule all my video calls in that time
of day when i know that i'm less
productive
so i'll have a scattering of calls and
catching up and then i'll have lunch
or i'll leave i'll leave the house and
i'll go have lunch like
at the coffee shop or something like
that and then i have this moment where
like i'm in the new location
and i get the coffee and then i open the
laptop and this is like the ceremony of
like now i am starting
new today you know yeah and uh and
anytime i start to feel kind of stuck or
useless or you know what i mean i
i like to do that kind of change in
location or
or or make the tea or make the coffee
and sit down and and then
okay now now this this three hour window
or this four hour window kind of begins
you know i i find that really helpful
yeah i guess when
if there are leaders that are scaling
back expectations and productivity
levels it
creates that space to sort of figure
that out as a remote worker because a
lot of people don't have that right now
with say
immediately with remote work
transitioning from
being in the office yeah the the a huge
thing is just cutting down on the zoom
meetings
really the more that you cut down on all
these stupid meetings
the more you give people their you give
people their time back
and then they can use that free time to
play
with their own schedule to figure out
what works for them and the thing is
once you figure out what works for you
in terms of what time of day you take
your calls and
and when you answer your mail and when
you do that focused work and
and all those different things and maybe
when you take the walk or when you take
the dog out or what these different
rituals are
once you figure that out then your
productivity can go really really high
you know you just need the chance to to
to rearrange the puzzle pieces until you
until they click into an arrangement
that
that works for you it's sort of like
shifting away from what you're used to
to figure out what works in this new
environment is is
kind of like somehow seems really
important from what you're saying
exactly it's a it's a design problem
it's an innovation problem
it's a how do i do this now that things
are different
but then you so you need to do some
experimentation and some trial and error
uh but then but then you figure it out
one more thing i wanted to ask is how do
you guys
have a company wide you know do you have
team events or anything like that uh how
do you actually
uh socialize with your other co-workers
get to know them outside of
the random one-on-ones is there anything
else deliberate that you guys do
yeah we have twice a year we have an all
hands company meetup
so everybody goes to the headquarters in
chicago and then we're all together for
a week so that's one thing
and then individually the different
teams also organize
so-called mini meetups that's where
everybody who's on ops or
you know a bunch of designers or
everybody who's working on the mobile
apps
will go somewhere for a week together
and those are amazing
because you know if you have 50 people
together you can't actually interact
with 50 people
you know but if you have 10 people
together
you can really spend some time and get
to know each other and have a lot of
exchange you know so
i think these mini meetups are really
fantastic yeah
okay right so um i want to wrap up is
there any final thoughts that you have
that you want to share with our
listeners
you know i think i think the main thing
to do is to
ask yourself before you reach out to
other people
what am i trying what am i trying to do
here
you know what is the what is the result
that i'm trying to get to
am i trying to get feedback on something
am i trying to get help on the solution
am i trying to frame the question
do i not know what to do do i not know
what's happening like what am i trying
to do
and then be more deliberate about the
format think about
if i reach out to somebody else right
now and i
ping them i'm actually trying to
interrupt them
right so if i do ping them
then i can write them in a way that says
hey when you have time
here's the thing that i would like a
response from you about or
you know maybe we could schedule some
time to talk error on the side of
clarifying what you're trying to do
more up front instead of just saying
let's get on the phone and then we're
going to talk it through
you know and and being more deliberate
about both the content
of the of the communication and the
format of the communication
has a massive multiplicative effect
right if you have a bunch of people and
they're all being more careful about how
they line things up for each other and
setting clear expectations about the
communication
then this has a massive multiplying
effect on the amount of free time
that everybody has yeah well uh ryan
it's been great having you on the show
again
thanks for coming and talking to us
about remote work at peace camp
excellent
this is akshay machaly for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
developers take your marks it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
it's time to deliver complex mission
critical applications in the fastest
route possible
it's time to use any data from any
source it's time to embed analytics and
create interactive user interfaces
so what are you waiting for choose your
language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster
and deploy more efficiently done and
done tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se se-radio.net to provide feedback you
can comment on each episode on the
website or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening